<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Practicall divinity: or a helpe through the blessing of God to lead men more to look within themselves, and to unite experienced Christians in the bond and fellowship of the Spirit. / Delivered in sundry exercises lately spoken by Cap. Paul Hobson, upon these texts. Published by an hearty wellwiller to peace and unity among the dissenting godly, and to the promotion of spirituall and experimentall truths, without affectation of opinions, or prejudice against persons. Tending as to the edification of the reader chiefly : so also, somewhat in vindication of the authour.</title>
            <author>Hobson, Paul.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86422</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2275</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1167_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208788</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867711</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867711</idno>
            <idno type="VID">120033</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86422)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 120033)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 166:E1167[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Practicall divinity: or a helpe through the blessing of God to lead men more to look within themselves, and to unite experienced Christians in the bond and fellowship of the Spirit. / Delivered in sundry exercises lately spoken by Cap. Paul Hobson, upon these texts. Published by an hearty wellwiller to peace and unity among the dissenting godly, and to the promotion of spirituall and experimentall truths, without affectation of opinions, or prejudice against persons. Tending as to the edification of the reader chiefly : so also, somewhat in vindication of the authour.</title>
                  <author>Hobson, Paul.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 122 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Licensed and published according to order. And sould by R. Harford at the Bible in Queenes-head-alley in Pater-noster-row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "A Taylor" is written in after the authors name; "Aprill 23th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Worship and love --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:120033:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Practicall Divinity:</hi> OR A HELPE THROVGH the bleſſing of God to lead men more to look within <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to unite experienced Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> in the bond and fellowſhip of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Delivered in ſundry exerciſes lately ſpoken by Cap. PAUL HOBSON, Upon theſe Texts.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.1.</bibl>
               <p>The righteous are as bold as a Lyon.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.9.</bibl>
               <p>My Dove, my undefiled is but one.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.11.</bibl>
               <p>I have learned in whatſoever eſtate I am therewith to be content.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed by an hearty Wellwillerto <hi>Peace and unity among the diſſenting Godly and</hi> to the promotion of ſpirituall and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall truths, without affectation or opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or prejudice againſt perſons. <hi>Tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as to the edification of the reader chiefly: ſo alſo, ſomewhat in vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the</hi> Authour.</p>
            <p>Licenſed and Publiſhed according to Order. And ſould by R. HARFORD at the <hi>Bible in</hi> Queenes-head-alley in Pater-noſter-row. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:120033:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:120033:2"/>
            <head>The Publiſher to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe Sermons allthough not intended by the Author to to be made thus publike, he being abſent when they were taken in hand; But being very much deſired by many and preſſed hereunto, conceiving truth herein held forth ſo cleare, that the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and experienced Chriſtian will relliſh and ſeale thereto; Being deſirous to owne truth whereſoever found, not daring to oppoſe it, truth carrying ſuch a light, power and demonſtration in it ſelfe,<note place="margin">James 2.1.</note> we durſt not have the faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt the Lord of glory in reſpect of perſons.</p>
            <p>It could be wiſhed the Author would publiſh his owne labours; but they appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to many, worthy the communicating,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:120033:3"/>they are here preſented to thy view; And although they may not be ſo full and emphaticall as they were delivered, being taken by writing them from his mouth, yet love will make thee not curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to ſpy faults, which is too common a fault in our times, but to take in good part what is here held forth to thee, by him who aimeth at thy ſpirituall good, and ſomewhat alſo in vindication of the Author of theſe Sermons, (whoſe I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they are, not only in regard of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion, but alſo in experience in a good meaſure) an imputation of errours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laid on him as on others, more then true.</p>
            <p>And indeed we beleeve as it was late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid before a ſolemne Aſſembly, <hi>there is (it may be) abroad a greater cry of errors then really there is, allthough with griefe be it ſpoken, there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny foule errors broached, and ſome very blaſphemous which deſerve as ſevere puniſhments as the word of God requires:</hi> yet let not reall and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:120033:3"/>glorious truths ſuffer under the name of error; Our Lord Chriſt himſelfe was counted among the tranſgreſſours, and St. <hi>Paul</hi> confeſſes after the way that yon call hereſie, ſo worſhip I the Lord God of my Fathers; and let us not judge all that error, which we by reaſon of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or not being come to the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences, cannot ſee to be truth; but let us try all things and hold faſt that which is good.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Neither as the Apoſtle ſaith ought we to <hi>boaſt of things without our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as the manner of ſome is,</hi> that is <hi>of other mens labours</hi> and experiences; <hi>in another mans line, of things made ready to our hand;</hi> for we are very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to think higher of our ſelves then is meet, or wee have cauſe,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.3 2 Cor. 10.17.</note> having built up our ſelves in our owne conceits, to be ſomething when we are nothing. That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Apoſtle Paul, Luther, &amp; others, through affliction and high experiences of Gods aſsiſtance, and thriving by the Croſſe, were tranſcendently hold in God
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:120033:4"/>and for God, therefore they are ready to appropriate and boaſt of their labours and experiences as if they were their owne, and were come to ſuch an high pitch and had the ſame enjoyments.</p>
            <p>But it were far better &amp; ſafer for us this <hi>ſomething were brought to nothing,</hi> and wee convinced of our owne weakneſſe ingrace and how carnall we are and how far below the life of Chriſt and true bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; This man ſhould goe home juſtified rather then the other. <hi>But he that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth let him glory in the Lord, that Chriſt may be all in all;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5 22.23.25.</note> 
               <hi>for not he that commendeth himſelf is approved, but whom the lord commendeth;</hi> for ſelf being ſet up and gotten into the chairt, it will ſwell, boasting itſelfe above what is meet, or what it hath received, and then others better then themſelves muſt be their footstoole, that by the degrading of others they may advance themſelves: <hi>but ſayes the Apoſtle, they that are Chriſts have crucified the fleſh with the affections and luſts; the fruit of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:120033:4"/>ſpirit is joy, peace, long ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, temperance; againſt ſuch there is no law; if we live in the ſpirit let us walke in the ſpirit, and let us not bee deſirous of vaine glory, provoking one another, envying one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But read I pray thee theſe Sermons ſeriouſly and with a ſingle eye, (if ſo it be given thee) and weigh the ſubject of them and whereto they tend, and apply them to experience: and thou ſhalt ſee how much or how little thou haſt of the life of Chirſt. And if thou beeft enabled to aime at thine owne good in peruſing them, I doubt not but thou wilt accept, and not quarrell at them. So I commend both them and thee to the bleſsing of him, who only is able to make us <hi>grow up into him in all things who is our head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>that ſpeaking the truth in love,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>and having fellowſhip in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; wee henceforth be no more chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>toſſed to and fro, and carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with every wind of Doctrine by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:120033:5"/>the ſleight of men, and cunning craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe whereby they lie in wait to deceive; But holding forth the word of life, till wee all come in the unity of the faith and knowledge of the ſon of God, unto a parfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of fullneſſe of Chriſt,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>In whom he deſires to ſerve thee, <hi>Fare well.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:120033:5"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eareſt <hi>friends,</hi> that which I purpoſe to ſpeake this morning very briefly, that I may give way to our Brother that is to ſpeak alſo, ſhall be out of the 28. <hi>Prov.</hi> part of the 1 ver. <hi>But the righteous are as bold as a Lyon.</hi> It will be neceſſary that wee read the foregoing words in regard of this word <hi>But,</hi> having ſome reference to ſome what ſaid before <hi>the wicked flee when none purſueth, but the righteous are as bold as a Lion;</hi> moſt of the ſentences in this book of the <hi>Prov.</hi> are without any dependence, but are intire ſpeeches, having their full ſence in themſelves; but here we have 2 ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences in one verſe, one explaining and ſetting out the other, two affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Propoſitions in oppoſition one to another; whatſoever can be ſpoken of a wicked man and one that lives from
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:120033:6"/>God, without God, the contrary in oppoſition may truly and properly be ſaid of a godly man, here called a <hi>righteous man,</hi> becauſe he lives in God, lives with God, he acts by the power of God, he lives in another Region, hath a contrary life, he is elemented in Divine loves, <hi>partakes of the Divine nature,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Peter 1.4.</note> and lives in the divine glory.</p>
            <p>Theſe words we have now read, they are an affirmation of a ſaints pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, and of a Saints property; All ſoules which are brought home to God, that live with God, this is their priviledge, they are made righteous by God; made righteous by Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a righteouſnes held out to them: and alſo made righteous by the glory and righteouſneſſe of God in them; and ſuch a man cannot chuſe but bee bold for ſuch a God; And not only bold in oppoſition to wicked men, becauſe <hi>they flee when none purſueth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 53.5.</note> 
               <hi>and feare where no feare is;</hi> but the higheſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of the higheſt creature, is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:120033:6"/>too low to ſet out what ſuch a mans boldneſſe is in God and for God, and therefore you ſee the Holy Ghoſt makes uſe of the choyfeſt of all the creatures for courage and boldneſſe, to ſet out the temper of a ſaint, when he lives in God and God in him; nay the higheſt and moſt raiſed ſublimity in the creature is too low to ſet out the loweſt acts of a ſaints ſpirit.</p>
            <p>I may draw one point from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer words, of wicked mens feare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it leads to unfold the other points concerning a righteous mans boldneſſe. <hi>The wicked flees when none purſueth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> The Doctrine, <hi>That man that lives without God, although made by God, he is ſo far a man of feare and not of faith.</hi> But I ſhall let that goe, and come to the words intended; There is not onely a difference in the ſpirits of wicked and righteous men, but a direct oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the one acts all together downe-ward to the earth, to ſelf, to carnall,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:120033:7"/>low, and baſe ends; the other acts all-together upward to God, to heaven, to ſelf denyall, to high and pure ends.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Firſt obſerve, <hi>That the people of God are a righteous people.</hi> They are righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, not only in regard of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, that is a righteouſneſſe held forth and made out to us: but alſo in regard of that you call ſanctification, that is, a righteouſneſſe revealed in us; and this is peculiarly a ſaints privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; He not onely lives under life, but he lives in life, is life it ſelfe: I confeſſe it is a great and precious pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to live under life, to have and uſe Ordinances; but to have them and not live by them, nay, to have them and not to haue lives above them, this is below a ſaints priviledge; the world hath thus much priviledge; But the ſaints they uſe not onely the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but they are a meanes to put them into life; to make them one with life, they know what the Anoninting is, what the unction of the Father is.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:120033:7"/>But now if you aske me what is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ant by a righteous man? <hi>Anſ.</hi> Some take it to be meant of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe. <hi>The righteous are as bold as a Lyon,</hi> that is, (ſay they) Chriſt, for he onely is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and not any man, therefore he is cald <hi>the Lyon of the tribe of Judah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 5.5.</note> But my light ſayes, this a diſcription of a ſaints ſpirit, for there is nothing can be ſaid of Chriſt, but may all ſo be ſaid of Saints, as ſaints; for he lives in the ſame life with Chriſt, in the ſame region, in the ſame glory; nay he lives in the ſame Soveraignty and authority; is Chriſt a ſonne and heire of his fathers glory? So are all Saints, they partake of the ſame ſonſhip, the ſame inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; is Chriſt a King? ſo are the Saints, partakers of the ſame Kingſhip. Hath he put downe all rule and all au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and ſubjected all his enemies under his feer? ſo have the Saints, ſo farre as they live with and in Chriſt; they ſet their foot upon all their luſts, upon all the world: they are conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:120033:8"/>over Death and Hell, they have ſet their foot upon the very neck of Sathan. I know beloved there be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to this life, there is a dying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we come to this life; but this is certaine, as a Saint comes up to this life, ſo he puts downe Principalities, and Powers, when he lives as a ſaint he puts downe all rule and all autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that before he was ſubjected to and captivated under. And the very matter of Chriſts glory, the ſame for nature and kind, though not for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in this life, is a Saints portion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> The 2. Obſervation theſe words hold forth, is from this expreſſion of boldneſſ, <hi>the righteous are bold.</hi> Doct. <hi>That the people of God are a bold people, full of courage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> The 3, Doctrine, <hi>Men and women muſt of neceſsity be made righteous by Chriſt, before they can be bold and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious for Chriſt.</hi> All other boldneſſe is a falſe deceiving boldneſſe, except it proceed from hence; in that we are
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:120033:8"/>freed, ſet at liberty, made righteous by Chriſt, many are bold tis true; but tis no true boldneſſe, tis a preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous boldneſſe: there is a naturall bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and there is a legall boldneſſe, and there is a phariſaicall boldneſſe, boldneſſe of divers kinds; but this true reall, unconquerable, undeceaveable boldneſſe, is only to be had and injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the life of Chriſt, being made righteous by him, not only by a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe made out to us, but by a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe revealed in us.</p>
            <p>The next Obſervation is from the reſemblance here uſed. <hi>The righteous are as bold as a Lyon.</hi> Tis a compariſon taken from the higheſt, and choyſeſt of all Creatures for undaunted bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and courage, in that hee fears no creature, nothing can turne him out of his way; the holy Ghoſt upon every occaſion when he would ſet out the property and priviledges of Saints, he ſtill chuſes the choyſeſt of all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to ſet it out by; to ſet out of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:120033:9"/>what a high, choiſe and raiſed ſpirit a Saint is off, as he is a Saint: the high frame of a Saints ſpirit that lives with Chriſt, is not to be ſet out by the choiſeſt of all the creatures, and that may be <hi>next</hi> the point.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Doctrine, <hi>That the higheſt of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is too low to declare the glory of a Saints ſpirit.</hi> Tis impoſſible by the choiſeſt of all creatures, &amp; by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of all creatures, to make it out to men in the full glory, beawty &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency thereof; He that injoyes it knowes it beſt, but he is not able to comprehend it; for he is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by it. And therefore he himſelf is not able to make it out to the full, but is ſwallowed up by it.</p>
            <p>Theſe pointes the words hold forth to us; but I ſhall not handle them ſeverally, but we will rather chuſe to gather the full ſence of them all in one concluſion, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That Soules made righteous by God are in the injoyment of God tranſcen
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:120033:9"/>dently bold.</hi> Here are 3 concluſions in one. 1. Here is Saints are made righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. 2. Saints thus made righteous they are bold. 3. They are tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently bold. For the opening this point, we muſt open all the words.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To be made righteous what it is. We ſhall not now ſpeake how we are made righteous by juſtification, as righteouſneſſe is purchaſed for us, and held out to us. Becauſe I conceive the words intend a man in the other ſenſe; a man made righteous, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing of righteouſneſſe in us, in that we are made one with the life and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Chriſt: we ſpeak now of a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſpirit, a freed ſpirit, a ſpirit made one with Chriſt, a ſpirit overcome in the enjoyment of Chriſts ſpirit, a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit wrapt up, overwhelmed by the ſweet inflowings and comings in of the glory of Chriſt: a ſpirit wherein Chriſt ſits in glory and diſplayes his loves to the ſoule, ſo that by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry coming in and injoyment of Chriſt,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:120033:10"/>they are made one with Chriſt, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into the very nature and glory of Chriſt. So that all ſelfe and the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry forme of the old creature is annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, and all turned into Chriſt; Hee is removed from his former center, his owne bottom; there is a new ingraft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and being carried up into Chriſt, ſo that he is transformed into the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, divine, ſuperexcellent glory and riches and life of Chriſt: ſo as he is (as I may ſay) chriſted with Chriſt, made glory with the very glory of God and Chriſt, ſo that this they not onely know in their underſtandings, but have, feel, and enjoy it, and it works in them a life, and fruit ſutable to this glory and transformation.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that lie in the heart of Chriſt, that have found themſelves transplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from themſelves, transformed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, by Chriſt, they finde their heart transformd with loves &amp; raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments towards him, to him, and none elſe, but as they ſee them, and enjoy
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:120033:10"/>them in him, and him in them; there are intercourſes &amp; returnes of love to each other. This is not the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Juſtification, when Chriſt holds out a righteouſneſſe purchaſed for thee, and thou by faith laying hold on it for the acceptation of thy perſon; but this is Chriſt himſelfe; his hand ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hold of thee, bringing thee over from thy ſelfe into himſelf, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting thee into himſelfe, and this is that that cauſes interchanges of loves, ſo that Chriſt in loving thee, he loves himſelf; and thou in loving him loveſt thy ſelfe, in one and the ſame act; and in all your acts Chriſt acts, and in all Chriſt acts within you, you act; ſo ſoone as ever you are brought over in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe injoyments, you are ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in Chriſt, and in your loweſt acts Chriſt acts as well as in your higheſt; in the very loweſt eſtate, you may have the higheſt injoyments: that when you are trampled on by the world, when your enimies think they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:120033:11"/>have got the day and have their will of you, then may you have ſuch ſweet injoyments of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.11.12.</note> that in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard you may <hi>rejoyce and be exceeding glad when you enter into divers temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jeames 1.2.</note> when the world and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors thinke they have taken from you all your comfort, and bereft you of all your life, then may you be more then conquerers, injoying a life hidden from them; that when they think you are captived, they themſelves are cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tived, and you the conquerers, <hi>as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.8.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>and yet true (ſayes the Apoſtle) as unknowne; yet well knowne; as ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>yet alway rejoycing; as poore, yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king many rich: as having nothing and yet poſſeſsing all things: you are dead to the world, but your life is hid with Chriſt in God;</hi> by this you may take a ſight and ſmall taſt of what is meant by a righteous man in this place, <hi>the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous are as bold as a Lyon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, what is meant by this word bold; truly friends I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:120033:11"/>I have been along time miſtaken what this bold ſpirit in a ſaint was; I tooke it to be this, and that, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in all; time was when I had a naturall boldneſſe which many men have, which is borne with them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a reſolute bold hardy temper of ſpirit; yet this was diſcovered to me to be but nature; and many a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man is poſſeſſed thereof: then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward I came to be a civill man; then in that I paid every man his owne, and lived uprightly to menward, ſo that no man could taxe me of doeing any man wrong; herein I grew bold; But this alſo was diſcovered to be but ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill boldneſſe, and upon falſe grounds. Then I came to Legall boldneſſe, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to ſuch a degree of obedience to the Law, that I thought my ſelfe all moſt blameleſſe, and herein I grew bold indeed, and I thought it was true boldneſſe: but it was diſcovered this was not the true boldneſſ neither, and there is many other kinds of boldnes;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:120033:12"/>there is a ſinfull boldneſſe, men being ignorant of themſelves, and what ſinne is, and what God is; they are bold to ſinne, and ſinne with a high hand daringly, with brazen faces. So alſo there is a phariſaicall boldneſſe, when men are bold becauſe of their externall conformity to the Law, and externall ſubmitting to Ordinances, becauſe they are in a right Goſpell way, becauſe they are of a fellowſhip where they injoy pure Ordinances; And am not I (ſay they) as good as you, what doe you more then I? I doe not ſpeake this that you ſhould neglect Ordinances, and forſake fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, for I know the High God may be injoyed in a low Ordinance; And you ought alſo to hold forth God in Ordinances to others, to men of the World, and Saints below you; though you injoy that which is farre above all Ordinances, even the reall and lovely preſence of the Lord Chriſt in himſelfe.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:120033:12"/>
            <p>Many men becauſe they injoy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in puritie, and hold forth a great Profeſſion, they gather hence a great boldneſſe, and looke bigg upon themſelves, and think who may walke more bigg, bold, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident then they (what, they not Saints? who is a ſaint then?) I that have gon thus ſarre, and tied my ſelf conſtant to duty, what not I of thus long ſtanding? But beloved, none of all theſe is the true boldneſſe; a Saints boldneſſe is from other principles, of a more noble and higher frame; His boldneſle is, becauſe he lives with, and injoyes the higheſt God: In that they are gotten above all the world. Things below are too baſe for their ſpirits; they count it gain to loſe themſelves: the other count it gain to gaine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; And hence it is, becauſe they ſee themſelves gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> above all things, they live undaunted noble lives; They live in the upper Regions where Chriſt lives, above all things inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:120033:13"/>to himſelf.</p>
            <p>They are ſo much drawne into Chriſt, that they cannot much minde theſe things below, they are not much troubled how they ebb or flow, becauſe they are aloft; They are not tumbled to and fro, as they in their Tides tumble too and againe; They are fild with noble bloud, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine bloud; the Spirit and Glory of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>God,</hi> reſts upon them, and runs in all their veines.</p>
            <p>Beloved, what can that man feare, that is thus tranſacted, tranſplanted, united to God, drawne up into God, in whom all ſelfe, and fleſh, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ends,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9.</note> is periſhed, dead and buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and he made a new man in Chriſt, riſſen in, and with Chriſt? Here is the man is here ſpoken of; Here is the boldneſſe of a Saint: No marvell all the world, nor all the fluctuation of and in the world, cannot diſturbe this mans Spirit; for he is above all, aloft, he is in the boſome of Chriſt;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:120033:13"/>Oh deareſt friends, this life is a hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thing, and you that injoy it know it, and none elſe; I know your experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of this life, farre exceed what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my tongue can expreſſe; when men have impriſoned you, and thinke they have overcome you, then are you moſt at liberty; When they have brought you to poverty, then have they moſt in richt you; when ye die, ye live; when you have all things, then have you nothing;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>when you have nothing, then have you all things;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.8.</note> you are ſo taken up with Chriſt, that all below Chriſt, <hi>is as droſſe, and dung,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.14.</note> and you ſay with Paul <hi>God forbid that I ſhould rejoyce in any thing, ſave in the Croſſe of Chriſt, by whom the world is crucified unto mee, and I unto the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While you are with Chriſt, what can hurt you? all the troubles in the world ſeaſe no more on you then wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on a Ducks back.; While the world is reviling, you are ſinging;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:120033:14"/>while the world is impriſoning, you are imbracing; While the world is hating and perſecuting, you are lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; While the world is caſting you off for ſects and ſciſmaticks, you are in your injoyings; While the world ſmites, Chriſt is kiſſing: ſuch a myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hidden ſecret, is the life of a ſaint, that it befooles all the world. When the world thinks they deſerve their hatred, they love and pittye them; while you think they look upon you, they looke above you; their eye is not upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their oppoſers, but what they injoy from Chriſt; they are of more noble, higher ſpirits, then to faſten their eyes ſo low as upon their oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers; I profeſſe when God brought mee of from one condition of bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to another; but eſpecially when hee fetcht mee off from legall and phariſaicall boldneſſe; in ſo much that I ſaw, that all boldneſſe which had its riſe and birth, in ſelf, from ſelf, and to ſelf, it muſt bee confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:120033:14"/>and I came to ſee that all true boldneſſe muſt run out from the very heart and loves of Chriſt; it muſt bee from a ſpirit fild with ſuch royall, noble, divine bloud, as none but the ſonnes of God pertake of; and then I ſaw the world was of a bloud ſo low and baſe, that it cannot bee ſenſible what this life is.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing we would come to ſhew, is, wherein this boldneſſe dothco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt. A ſoule thus made one with God, made righteous by God in the injoyment of God, and by the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God revealed in us, he is bold in theſe three regards.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He is bold with God. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, He is bold in declaring for God. Thirdly, He is bold in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going any thing laid upon him by God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He is bold with God, he is free and familiar with God; There is ſuch intimate communion between Chriſt and him, that he can freely,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:120033:15"/>and with a ſonlike ſpirit and affection, ask any thing of God, his enjoyments embolden him; For he ſees God ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſome himſelf to him, that his <hi>very</hi> heart is not too much for him. Hee asks not as a ſervant with ſlaviſh fear, but as a ſonne, as ſeeing all his inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance is in God. He knowes what ever is in God, in Chriſt, is as freely his as they are Chriſts; he hath as true right to them as Chriſt; Hee layes claime to all the beawties and glories of Chriſt, to all the riches, life, and treaſures in Chriſt, as his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per portion. He does not aske with a daunted fearfull ſpirit, he approaches into his very Boſome, to his very Heart: and what ever is there, hee knows is his owne to aske and injoy; and this he does freely, fully; he layes claime to all Divine loves.</p>
            <p>And by this injoyment, he makes returnes of loves; all the loves his heart can hold, ſhall all run out to God againe; by this very imbracement, he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:120033:15"/>comes to act in God and God in him.</p>
            <p>And I pray you obſerve this, and think of it when you do not ſee mee; The very injoyment of God carries o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your ſpirits, &amp; all you are to God, to give up your ſelves to him; you will not ſtand upon ſuch needleſſe que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions. Whether ſaints are bount to duty; they by that very act of injoying God, make themſelves over to God, to be acted, and ruled by God: their owne will ceaſes, and Gods will is become one with theirs, and theirs with his; you cannot chuſe but love &amp; act for God, for you are with God, in God:</p>
            <p>Friends, I hope ſome of your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits doe eccho to theſe truthes, and finde them true, by your injoyments in ſome degree. Doe not thinke that this is the life you muſt look for on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hereafter, when you are come to Heaven after this life; I tell you this life is now, and I verily beleeve the time is coming, that ſaints ſhall come
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:120033:16"/>to ſee this life made good to them, and in them more and more.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But it may be ſome will ſay, you ſpeak of a very high life; is it poſſible that ſuch poore Creatures, ſuch poore Wormes as we are, ſhould be ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced by the Eternall God? How comes this to paſſe?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In three regards the Saints have experience of theſe things. Firſt, In regard they know they have a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in him. Secondly, In regard they have knowledge in experience of recourſe to him. Thirdly, of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant familiarity with him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, They have a knowledge of propriety in him, they know that God hath made himſelfe their Father, and they his ſons, this makes them bold; who can be more bold with a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then his ſonnes? <hi>Though Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham be ignorant of us, yet thou art our Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſal. 63.16.</note> 
               <hi>behold we come unto thee, for thou art the Lord our God.</hi> They know God does not caſt them off becauſe of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:120033:16"/>their ſins; this does not make them no ſons, but they look upon God as an infinite gracious loving Father; They have experience, that coming to their Father is a meanes to purifie their hearts, and if they ſtand off till they have clenſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves, this has been a means to throw them more into ſin; and though they have ſinned, yet they throw themſelves into his armes, they have experience that he dos not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid them for coming to him, in ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves, how durſt they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to him, being ſo defild with ſin; But they finde, that bringing their hearts to him, is the only way to cleanſe themſelves; they finde ſuch loves in the boſome of the Father, ſuch bowels to pardon, ſuch embracements, that they know no way in all the world comparable to this, to breake their hearts, and to make them throw ſin far away. Time was when they ſaid, true it is, Chriſt calls, and invites mee to come, but I am ſo defiled, ſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:120033:17"/>ſinfull, I dare not come: I will reforme my life, and get more power againſt ſin, and then I may goe with boldnes.</p>
            <p>But this ſoule who hath injoyed the loves of God, ſo ſweetly, ſo intimate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he findes this is the way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine foule ſtill; And though hee might refraine ſin, yet he was not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from ſin; This end, and that end wrought with him; ſomething from ſelf, and to ſelf: but ſin as ſin was as ſtrong as ever. But he found this way the only way to heale ſinne, and get a new heart, a new nature, <hi>viz.</hi> to throw himſelf upon his <hi>Father,</hi> into his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> armes: <hi>Though Abraham be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 63.16.</note> 
               <hi>yet thou art our Father;</hi> And this going to God frees us from our ſinnes, and nothing elſe. To ſay I am legall, and I am full of corruption, I am weake and I can doe nothing: all this while, we ſtand at a diſtance, and weaken our ſelves more; We are not free, we are lockt up in our ſelves, and ſtrive by our own ſtrength. But if you
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:120033:17"/>would be holy, throw your ſelves into the loves of <hi>God;</hi> this very injoyment will give you an inlarged, a free, and broken <hi>heart;</hi> then ſin will be hated from a new <hi>nature.</hi> God dos not ſay I love you, if you be <hi>holy;</hi> but, I love you to make you <hi>holy.</hi> Beloved, this is the <hi>new covenant</hi> that the <hi>Goſpell</hi> holds out to us; and herein lies the power of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> to make of <hi>unrighteous, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> to work by love, not by conſtraint.</p>
            <p>Men that never had experience of this life, they lay Lawes, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints upon men to duty, and know not the power of love. When the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall</hi> had but a reſolution to throw himſelf upon his fathers loves, you ſee how he was received; No ſooner dos God open his heart to a poore ſinner, but he ſees the everlaſting roling bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of a <hi>Father,</hi> toward him, and then they interchange loves and bowels;<note place="margin">Hoſ. 11.8.</note> 
               <hi>That their repentings are kindled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 31.22.</note> 
               <hi>I doe earneſtly remember him ſtill: my bowels are troubled for him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 3.22.</note> Bowels
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:120033:18"/>role towards one another, and then the poore ſinners come to ſee their own names writ in their own hearts, that before was writ in the heart of God; And ſee his deareſt loves have ever been toward them for good; He ſees now he was not excluded from God, becauſe he had departed away from him, and blackſliden, but was the rather cald to come to him, becauſe hee had blackſlided, and defiled himſelfe;<note place="margin">Jer. 3.22</note> As Jer. 3.22. <hi>Returne ye backſliding children, and I will heale your backſlidings; Behold we come unto thee, for thou art the Lord our God.</hi> He has experience that he had laine long ſtriving againſt ſin, but found no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from a right ground, from a right principle; But when he (it may be) after many years ſtriving with his luſts to ſubdue them, and bring them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he reſolved at laſt to goe to God and ſaid: Lord here is my heart, as bad as can be, the more I ſtrive with it, the worſe it is; I have ſtriven long and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:120033:18"/>cannot conquer one ſinne; but Lord doe thou now take it, doe with it what thou will; all this while <hi>I</hi> was aſham'd to come to thee, my heart was ſo bad; now I commit it to thee; and then hee found a ſubdued heart, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver before.</p>
            <p>So long as I look upon my obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and my conformity, and when I ſee a want, I hold off from God; this breedes obſtructions between the ſoule and God. Your praying, and your duties, and your obedience, doe declare that you live in God, and not that they may bring you to God.</p>
            <p>Brethren, this is the way: have you finned and falen from God? ſtay not but returne to God, <hi>then he will heale your backſliding;</hi> Stay not, as men u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually doe, till your ſelves have hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led your own backſlidings, and then you will beleeve. This way doth never rightly overcome the heart; but be ye weake Chriſtian, or be ye ſtrong, try this way, and you ſhall find
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:120033:19"/>a wonderfull change in your ſpirits; you may draw nigh to God, with boldneſſe, the way ſtands open; God never chid a ſoule that throwes it ſelf upon him.</p>
            <p>Againe, this often recourſe to, and familiarity with God, it makes a man rightly to underſtand God, to know his very nature; men that live out of God, miſtake God; they judge other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of his nature then it is; Saints by injoying God, they know God; what a God of ſweetneſſe and loves he is; how free in communicating of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; what an unchangable God he is; how ready to receive a ſinner; what loves run from him into them, when once they are come in to him; though God frowne, they know his nature is nothing but unchangeable loves; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he deales with them in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, they know all his wayes are wayes of love to them; He cannot hate them, nor doe any thing as a fruite of hatred; They underſtand
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:120033:19"/>God, they know his wayes with his Saints; <hi>though he kill them, yet will they truſt in him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 55.</note> Though in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Providence hee ſeemes to frowne, yet they know whats in his heart; they take all in good part their Father doth unto them.</p>
            <p>This is that which raiſes up their hearts to a holy boldneſſe of ſpirit; What ever men intends they know God ſmiles; what ever his providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are, they know his loves are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, unchangable; This makes their hearts rejoyce, and triumph, to live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove; though the body be under ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, yet their ſpirit is free; walkes up and downe in loves, is compaſſed about with joyes, ſwallowed up in GOD, and lives amongſt Divine Crownes.</p>
            <p>If a man have no experience of theſe things, he lives darkly, mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, he meaſures God by himſelf; if men be angry, he thinks God is angry; if providence change, they think God
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:120033:20"/>changes; and this raiſes not, but over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmes the ſpirit of a man; this ſinks his ſpirit; for he judges God like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; but what ſayes God? <hi>are my wayes as your wayes, and my thoughts, as your thoughts?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 55.</note> 
               <hi>As high as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens are above the Earth: ſo high are my thoughts above your thoughts, and my wayes above your wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly they are bold for God; ye never ſee any principle, but it works ſutable to itſelf; ſo the Saints have a principle from God, which qualifies them ſo, that they can ſtand for God: 1. In ſuffering for him; if it be his will, they ſhall ſuffer loſſes, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny, deriſion, yea Death it ſelf, they have a principle from God will beare them out; Look upon <hi>Paul,</hi> what a ſpirit had he when they told him of bonds?<note place="margin">Acts. 21.13.</note> 
               <hi>what meane ye to weepe and breake my heart? for I am ready (ſayes he) not only to be bound, but to die for the name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo the three Children, what
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:120033:20"/>reſolutions had they to ſuffer? <hi>Wee know our God whom wee ſerve,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 3.17.18.</note> 
               <hi>is able to deliver us, but howſoever be it known unto thee, wee will not worſhip this Image;</hi> Frownes, nor ſcornes from men, will not turne them out of their way.</p>
            <p>And the reaſons of this are, Firſt, the reall conviction of ſecurity in God, before they ingage themſelves for God; as 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. <hi>For which cauſe I alſo ſuffer theſe things; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe I am not aſhamed, for I know in whom I haue beleeved, and I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded he is able to keepe that which I have committed to him, againſt that day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſoule ſeeing God ſuch a buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and ſeeing himſelfe ſo ſecure; this makes him not ſtand at any thing, but to ingage himſelfe and all he is for God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But you will ſay then, this is but ſelf-love: not to ingage, but that hee knowes he|ſhall be ſecure.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:120033:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I anſwer no,</hi> tis not ſelfe love, but love to God. But here lies a great myſterie, in a Saints thus ingaging for God.</p>
            <p>It ariſes from being partaker of the very nature of God; and his will is ſo ſwallowed up and reſigned into Gods that he acts Gods will, not his own; So that his ſecurity is not in any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward protection, but in what the will of God is? and if his ſpirit live in, and with God, what ever fall to him, this he accounts his ſecurity.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rea. </seg>2</label> Every ſpirit acts ſutable to that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit it is in conjunction with; Now Chriſts ſpirit, is the moſt noble, moſt high, moſt raiſed ſpirit; and the ſpirit that is in Chriſt, is in the Saints; their ſpirits are in conjunction with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt; therfore they muſt needs be of noble, high, &amp; raiſed ſpirits; that though they be in the fleſh, their life is in the Spirit, their life is in Chriſt; though they have thornes and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the fleſh, yet to them they are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:120033:21"/>as none; they are not much troubled at them, for their ſpirits live among divine thrones and Crownes.</p>
            <p>The 3. reaſon of a Saints thus boldly ingaging for God, is, Though they ſuffer externally, yet there is within a ſupply of contrary love; and ſmiles;</p>
            <p>Men indeavorto throw ſcornes, and deriſions upon the Saints; and invent ſuch deriding names, that they would make them odious: even as the very offscouring of the World, and that they may render them as the vileſt men upon earth.</p>
            <p>It matters not, God viſits them with his loves; Hee communicates that to their ſpirits, which abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly makes up their ſuffering, and makes amends a thouſand thouſand times.</p>
            <p>One comes and he calls you Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, another Independents, another Sciſmaticks, another Anabaptiſts, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Antinomians, another comes and tells you, they are this day go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to petition the <hi>Parliament</hi> againſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:120033:22"/>all your <hi>Independents;</hi> now what of all this? were you but carried above, and did you live in God? theſe would be like ſo many ſmall puffes of wind that would ſcarſe blow away a ſtraw; For a man never feares a man, when hee knowes himſelfe above a man; when he knowes himſelfe free from him, and out of his reach to hurt him.</p>
            <p>All the men in the World cannot hurt a Saint; nor all the Divells in Hell; a man will never feare his Enemie, eſpecially when he knowes he is kild before hee comes neare him.</p>
            <p>Chriſt hath overcome ſin, Death, Hell, the Divell, the World; and therefore, what need the ſaints feare any of theſe?<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>The afflictions of this life are but light and momentary: but there is an exceeding weight of glory to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed.</hi> Will a man regard a ſmall croſſe, when he has a weight and an exceeding weight of Divine loves, of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:120033:22"/>Divine Crownes?</p>
            <p>This is enough to make a man, not only to be content to beare afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and frownes from the World; but alſo to love the croſſe, to love the frownes.</p>
            <p>When thou haſt a loſſe in thy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, in thy name, or any way, Chriſt comes with his loves, and makes an over abundant ſupply; I doe not ſay; he gives thee the ſame things; but, he gives thee that which is a thouſand times more worth.</p>
            <p>If thou loſeſt farthings, and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt pounds; if thou loſeſt ſtrawes and gaineſt pearles, what loſſe haſt thou?</p>
            <p>Thus Chriſt doth to a Saint at the very inſtant of his ſuffering, if he live with &amp; in Chriſt; for Chriſts way is, not to ſend the affliction and let it lie heavie, and preſſe a man downe, and then he afterwards lets men reaſon themſelves into content; for a Saints content, as a Saints, is not from rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but from a preſent injoyment of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:120033:23"/>Chriſt, which is communicated at that very inſtant, immediatly from the very boſome and heart of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Intercourſes of loves runnes out from Chriſt; which alone is their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, without reaſons helpe.</p>
            <p>The fourth Reaſon, why the Saints are ſo bold in declaring, and ingaging for God is; becauſe, in all their ſufferings, they ingage not at their own coſt and charges; they live not by their own life, they live not by their owne ſtrength; but they ingage at Chriſts charges, &amp; they live by Chriſts life, they ſpend upon his ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Ti's a Phraſe wee have often up, eſpecially in the Country; they may ſpend freely that ſpend upon other mens Purſes.</p>
            <p>So the Saints, they goe on in their way, and walke like Saints, becauſe they live not by and of themſelves; their life, and their ſtrength, and their comforts, are all Chriſts; they ſpend
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:120033:23"/>upon his Stock.</p>
            <p>This makes them ſo free and ſo bold, ſpend while they will, they have a vaſt Treaſure, never to bee exhauſted; Still Chriſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes them with new ſtrength, and new life.</p>
            <p>Let men goe on to revile and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the Saints, and ſtudy names of Factions, and <hi>Independents</hi> and the like, to make them odious; No mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Chriſt aſſiſts them; Chriſt hath names full of Love and ſweetneſſe for them.</p>
            <p>And if they ſhould proceed to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution as they may, and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, no matter; There comes a new ſuppy from Chriſt anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their ſufferings.</p>
            <p>But the Saints being weake and not knowing this, they many times needleſlly trouble themſelves with forethinking what they ſhall doe, if Suffering, and Afflictions, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:120033:24"/>Troubles increaſe; And the reaſon is, becauſe they apply, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare Future Troubles to preſent ſtrength.</p>
            <p>But thoſe that live in Chriſt, and with Chriſt, they know they cannot ingage upon any new affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, But there is a new ſupply of Strength, and Courage, and life from Chriſt; and therefore they reaſon thus.</p>
            <p>If Bonds, Reproaches, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, or Death it ſelfe doe attend mee; There is Freſh Joy, New Life, and more Srength at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends.</p>
            <p>The more oppoſers, the more Strength, the more Joy, the more Glory, the more Loves, the more Imbraces, The more overcomings of Loves.</p>
            <p>And therefore this is that which makes them Bold in Declaring for God.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:120033:24"/>
            <p>Who more bold for God in decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring truth then the Apoſtles, in <hi>Acts</hi> the fourth? though they knew trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and perſecution attended them,<note place="margin">Acts: 4.10.</note> and bonds in every place, <hi>be it knowne ſaith</hi> Peter <hi>unto you and to all Iſraell, that by the name of Ieſus Chriſt of</hi> Nazareth <hi>was this man made whole, whom ye crucified, but God hath raiſed him up, and this is the ſtone ſet at naught by you Builders and is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the head of the corner, neither is there Salvation in any other; Now when they ſaw the boldneſſe of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and ſaw that they were ignorant men, they tooke knowledge that they had beene, with Ieſus, and could ſay nothing againſt the Miracle they had wrought in the name of Ieſus; Then they tooke counſell and ſtreightly charged them they ſhould ſpeak no more in that name, and they anſwered boldly, whether is it right in ſight of God to hearken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you more then unto God, Iudge yee? for we can not but ſpeake the things we
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:120033:25"/>have ſeene and heard:</hi> and ſo the whole Chapter, and divers other places do declare, with what wonderfull bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe they declare Chriſt; becauſe Chriſt lived withthem, lived in them, they had experience of his ſtrength and love in ſupporting. And their love could not but returne in decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the things they had ſeene and heard.</p>
            <p>And the Reaſons of this are, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the injoyment of theſe things beget a love to the things declared, &amp; gives power to declare them with all courage and boldnes; the Saints are made one with Chriſt, ſuckt and drawne up into Chriſt, they live by loving and love by living, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare through loving, &amp; love through declaring. And ſutable to their love they cannot chooſe but declare, love in them hath the preheminence, it predominates, it over-rules all other things in them, they muſt needs, they are conſtrained to declare the life they live in.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:120033:25"/>
            <p>If a Parliament ſhould command, that men ſhould not declare what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience they have of Chriſt, as I hope this Parliament never will, they could not contayne, it would be as fire in their boſomes, it would burſt out, loves would ſo conſtraine them; could they ſit and ſee and not ſpeake? I tell you there is ſuch mighty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraines in the power of love, they could not keepe in.</p>
            <p>It bootes not the World to act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the power of love to raiſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, the more they act againſt it the more it workes, the more it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraines.</p>
            <p>Againe another reaſon is, why they are ſo conſtrained to declare what they ſee and know, becauſe the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter declared is the very power decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. They are ſo lapt up in the loves of Chriſt &amp; ſo made one in him, that the things they declare is not another thing from them, but they are the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:120033:26"/>
            <p>And therefore if they are ſo bold in declaring, <hi>never blame them,</hi> for they and thoſe things are the ſame; no nor <hi>never admire them,</hi> for there is ſuch a conſtraining power in them they cannot do otherwiſe. And that he hath he receives not from others as their experiences, but they are his owne, they are himſelfe. <hi>Paul</hi> (you ſee) when once Chriſt had appeared to him, there was ſuch a Light, ſuch a Glory, ſuch a Power, ſuch a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of Truth to his Soule, that he immediately went &amp; preacht Chriſt; he went not to the Bretheren to be confirmed in what he ſaw and felt, but the power love was ſuch, that come life come death he muſt declare it.</p>
            <p>And a third Reaſon may be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he enjoyes what he declares; what he enjoyes he acts, and what he acts he enjoyes; while he ſaies he ſees he feeles; while he ſpeakes of love, he acts in love.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:120033:26"/>
            <p>Here now you ſee the quality of a Saints ſpirit. And indeed this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and enjoying <hi>he</hi> eſteemes his protion, his everlaſting inheritance, his Heaven; his very worke is his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <hi>eſteeming</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>the reproach with Chriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.26</note> greater rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es then the Treaſures of</hi> Egypt,<note place="margin">Phil 4.8.</note> this life was the <hi>recompence of reward</hi> Moſes <hi>had an eye too,</hi> and Paul <hi>he counted all things loſſe and dung,</hi> to gaine &amp; enjoy it; and <hi>David herejoyceth in the word as one that findeth great ſpoiles,<note place="margin">Pſ. 16.5.6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> for in keeping thereof, there is a full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beloved freinds this is your Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and if you cannot count this a ſufficient Heaven and reward, you will hardly thinke Heaven hereafter a reward, eſpecially in the condition you are in; but did you act in love and lived in Chriſt here, you would ſay were this life but perfected, I have enough, enough; I deſire no other Heaven, this portion is enough; as
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:120033:27"/>
               <hi>David</hi> ſaies in 16 <hi>Pſalme.<note place="margin">Pſ. 16.5.6.</note> The Lord is the portion of mine Inheritance, the Lines are fallen to me in very pleaſant places, yea I have a Goodly Heritage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we come to the Third thing wherein the Saints are bold: They are bold in undergoing any thing from God; muſt I be poore, muſt I be ſicke, muſt I be in priſon, muſt I be in Death, he is bold to undergoe it; he ſees the loves of God in all that comes to him: Let all the world con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn together againſt this man, and looke never ſo blacke and terrible up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, he ſees his God ſmileing, his God ſpeaking nothing but loves.</p>
            <p>As ſinne and the law, though they are in conjunction to terrifie him, yet he is bold, for he ſees God recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled. And as they (the greater) can not daunt his boldnes, ſo neither can men, nor can the Word, all they can doe cannot make him thinke his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is angry.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:120033:27"/>
            <p>Though God himſelfe try the Saints; they liveing in him, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying his love; Though he ſeeme in his Providence to be angry; yet they find loves in his very boſome, in his very heart, when men enjoy not this, every frowne from men, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very frowne from God, caſts them downe; they forſake their boldnes, becauſe they have no exprience of the ſweet and unchangeable nature of God. as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.14.<note place="margin">Exek. 22.14.</note> 
               <hi>Can thine heart endure, or can thine hands be ſtrong in the daies that I ſhall deale with thee:</hi> They being backſliden and departed from God they were not able to look on God as a father, when he aflicted them, as the Saints can doe; Doth God chide? yet they know tis in love. Doth God wound? all are fruits of his love.</p>
            <p>So now you ſee how bold a Saint is with God; How bold in ſtanding for God; How bold in declaring God, How bold in undergoing any thing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:120033:28"/>from God; and all this by liveing with God, by liveing in God, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying God. This man muſt needs be a bold man that hath ſuch inflowings of loves from God; what ſhall ſuch a man account deere for ſuch a God? How bold was <hi>Jer.</hi> in the Priſon? though put in the Dungeon, where he ſanke in the mire and was ready to ſtarve? when he was taken out againe and remained in priſon, he could not hold his peace; the power of loves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained him to ſpeake what he had ſeene and felt.</p>
            <p>And ſo <hi>Iob</hi> though he was aflicted in his Eſtate, in his children, in his owne perſon,<note place="margin">Iob. 13.15.</note> what (ſaith he) <hi>though he kill me</hi> he deferves to be truſted in; I cannot forſake him for all this.</p>
            <p>And old <hi>Ely</hi> when there was ſuch bitter things ſpoken againſt him by God, ſaith he <hi>it is the Lord let him do with me what ſeemeth him good.</hi>
               <note place="margin">I Sam. 3.18.</note> And that is the higheſt Act that is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of him. And the reaſon is, becauſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:120033:28"/>that man that lives in God underſtands God in himſelfe, what his heart is. If we looke on God as he acts out of himſelfe and not as he acts in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, there is nothing but changes, to day ſicke, tomorrow well; to day in priſon, tomorrow not; this yeare rich, next yeare poore; Now if we ſhall judge that God changes as our condition changes,<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. 17.</note> what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort? But God in his nature is one &amp; the ſame, no changes <hi>nor ſhadow of turning,</hi> alwaies alike. Againe a ſaint in God lives in the will of God, Gods will is all in all to him. And this is that which brings him up to that rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe and height of ſpirit; he ſees God in what ever he doth to act his owne bleſſed will on him, and ſo he ſee but that accompliſhed, therein he reſts and rejoyces, becauſe he lives above aloft, he lives in the Center, in the Fountaine of loves. If we live in the ſtreames, if we live below among the Creatures, there is nothing but
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:120033:29"/>trouble and rumbling this way and that way, ebbing and flowing; but the Center, the Fountain, the upper Regions are quiet, ſtill, compoſed, ſattisfied. Againe, becauſe if God do take all from the Creature and take him up to live in himſelfe he hath not loſt all but found all a thouſand fold. Yet in the moſt rougheſt acting out of God. he finds loves in God; elſe his ſpirit would be downe to day and up to morrow, according to thoſe actings; but this life with God, in the boſome and bowells of tranſcendent loves, there <hi>all diſputs are at an ends,</hi> he lives in providence above provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, he lives above reaſons Region and Element, and therefore when Reaſon would make diſputes and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments from Gods externall deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; as if God were as rough as his providence; this life ſilences all, and layes the ſoule to reſt in the ſweet em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces of the loves of an unchainga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Father; <hi>though he kill me yet will I truſt in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:120033:29"/>
            <p>And againe the Saints have ſuch experience of the loves of God, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing warme from the heart of God that they cannot be beaten out of good thoughts of God: as we ſay by a freind whom we know and love &amp; have intimate acquaintance with; if this man or that ſhould bring tales of evill intended by him towards you; you would ſay I wil not beleeve him, for I know him ſo <hi>well that</hi> the thing is impoſſible to be true; So doe the Saints find God ſuch a true freind ſuch an intimate cloſe freind, that hath ſo much expreſt his love to them that though ſin, the Law, Hell, Death, the Divell, the World, Providence, or whoever ſhould bring them ill ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings from their father: ob (ſay they) it cannot be, I know him ſo well, I have ſuch ſweet ſuch frequent enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with him, that I cannot thinke a hard thought of him, this drawes up the Soule to a high, yea a higher and higher enjoyment of God.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:120033:30"/>
            <p>This enjoyment tranſcends yea ſleights all other enjoyments below it, it tranſcends Nature, it tranſcends Reaſon, it tranſcends externall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and all the rougheſt actings thereof. Let never ſo high accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be layd on the Saints, they va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue them not, their life with God makes up all; As ſome have laid di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers accuſations on me and on the Saints, ſome are Truths, and we are ready to maintaine them, we hope to the death; others are falſe and charging upon us that we never ſaid nor held, and all to make us odious to the World; As for inſtance that I ſhould ſay, there was no other uſe of Chriſt but to declare love to the World, and for this end he came and for no other. Who ever holds it for my part I count it an errour, my Judgment is otherwiſe, I hold no ſuch thing, I diſclaime it; Chriſt came to ſattisfie and anſwer a law, as well as to make out love; and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:120033:30"/>though theſe and the like, and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things may be fathered upon us, partly through darkenes, not ſeeing and enjoying Truth, &amp; partly through malice, to lay to our charge, the things we never knew nor held; yet we hope God will vindicate his Truth and vindicate his ſaints, and Truth ſhall burne and flame out ſo gloriouſly, that he will make all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers and ſlanderers aſhamed, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let not the ſaints much trouble themſelves at theſe things, let the Creature be ſtill and ſilent, and let God alone, he is but working a way for his owne praiſe, in confounding his enemies, and vindicating the ſimplicity of the ſaints, who live with him and in him to their everlaſting comfort and Joy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:120033:31"/>
            <p>BEloved freinds, that I intend to ſpeake unto you at this preſent, ſhall be from the word of God, in the 6 of <hi>Cant.</hi> 9 verſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Dove my undefiled is but one, ſhe is the only one of her mother, ſhe is the choice one of her that bare her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which I ſhall ſpeake to you at this time, ſhalbe only from the firſt words, <hi>My Dove my undefiled is but one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is not much dependance of theſe words on the foregoing words, but ſo much dependance there is, that as you may ſee in the former words, that the Daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of the Spouſe of Chriſt <hi>where her beloved is,</hi> ſhe had ſo ſet him out and expreſſed her ardent affection to him, that they begin to wonder &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee what a one her beloved was, becauſe ſhe was ſo raviſhed with him, ſay they in the firſt verſe, <hi>whether is
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:120033:31"/>thy beloved gone, oh thou faireſt among women, whether is thy beloved turned aſide that we may ſeek him with thee?</hi> ſhe anſwers them in the next verſes, <hi>My beloved is gon downe into his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, to the beds of ſpices, to feed in the Gardens and gather Lillyes. And I am my beloveds and my beloved is mine, he feedeth among the Lillies.</hi> And then Chriſt in the next words begins to diſcribe and ſet out what his Spouſe is, and anotomizes her in all her por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracture and beauties, not only how beutifull ſhe is to him and amiable through his beuty put upon her, but alſo how fruitfull his Spouſe is in the enjoying her beloved <hi>that ther's not one barren among them,</hi> ſo amiable every way that Chriſt was raviſhed with her beuty, therefore (ſaith he) <hi>turne away thine eyes from me for they have overcome me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then this diſcription might breed this objection, are all ſo beuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and comly? are all ſo fruitfull
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:120033:32"/>that there it not on barren amongſt them; they are ſeverall and of ſeverall tempers and judgements, nether do they all appeare ſo fruitfull as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes? he anſwers all in this ninth verſe <hi>My Dove my undefiled is but one,</hi> All Saints in Chriſt are but one; men of the world, and poore Saints, weak Saints, that ſee not their priviledges by Chriſt, they are ready to ſay how can this be, that the Spouſe of Chriſt is ſo beutifull ſo fruitfull, they ſee it otherwiſe, they can ſee no beuty in them, they bring forth but little weake and poore fruit, here is ſome of this way and ſome of that fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſome of this Judgement and ſome of that, ſome are in a Church way and ſome are not, ſome are Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregated and ſome are uncongrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I but for all that, though among themſelves they be divers, yet in Chriſt they are but one; You, 'tis true, make a difference but that ſhould not be, This is but the folly
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:120033:32"/>and weakneſſe of men, but ſee and looke upon them as they are in Chriſt, and you ſhall ſee they are one to him, as they are in him and live with him and in him, they are fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, though not as they are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The points that I apprehend theſe words hold forth are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Doct.</hi> That Chriſts Church is Chriſts Dove,</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>D.</hi> Chriſts Church is Chriſts undefiled Dove,</item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Doct.</hi> That Chriſts Church or Chriſts Dove is not divided but is one and united.</item>
               </list> Now for the firſt of theſe, if you aske why Chriſts Church is called Chriſts Dove: I conceive for preſent 'tis in two regards, firſt in regard of their Priviledges, how much they are ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by him: and ſecondly in regard they are made glorious and amiable by him. 1. Conſidering how precious they are to him, what affections he hath let out to them, the deareſt loves and the very heart of Chriſt runnes out to them, ſingly, ſolely, nothing
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:120033:33"/>that is in the very bowells and heart of Chriſt, is too good, too deare for them; there's nothing in Chriſt but is there laid up, kept and preſerved for a Saints treaſure; all the choice loves of God, the choiceſt life of God is treaſured up in Chriſt for his Saints; and when once they have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken themſelves, then to be enjoyed by them, and delighted in for ever; he thinkes nothing too good for his Spouſe: he hath not only filled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for them, but emptyed himſelfe for them, poured out his own bloud, his owne life, his owne glory to ſave them, to inrich them.</p>
            <p>Chriſt ſhewes how precious they are to him, firſt in regard of the place where he layes a ſaint, that is, in his very boſome, in his very heart; not only in his common providence, but in his very heart, he never leaves a ſaint, till he bring it from ſtep to ſtep by degrees into himſelfe; that the ſoule is ſo lapt up in him, that he hath
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:120033:33"/>made it one with himſelfe. And that ſoule that is acquainted with this life knowes this, and none elſe; others know not what it means, I was (ſayes he) a ſlave under the Law, and it ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannized over me; many a hard leſſon, and many a hard task I had ſet me, and many a bitter ſtripe; and hee in bowells of loves came and freed me, he redeemed me from that tyrannie; I was under the killing letter which threatned nothing but death and hell, and now I have found his loves in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me at liberty; and now I can read his loves in every line, in all his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and theſe are, I ſay, ſuch loves that none can prize, but thoſe that have them, read, ſeene, and felt them in them. This is a Saints por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion peculiarly to live with Chriſt, to live of Chriſt, to live in him. 'Tis the worlds portion to live under life, and not injoy life, but a ſaint lives in life; life and he are one; they are brought by Chriſt into the very over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowings
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:120033:34"/>of loves, they live in the very ſtreams of loves, compaſſed about with loves; Chriſt comes to them continually, ſups with them, wraps them up in admiration of himſelfe, and fills them with divine loves.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Chriſt declares how precious ſaints are to him, by taking all advantages to do them good, by ſin, by ſorrowes, by ſufferings, by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, by life, by death, every way; none of all theſe but Chriſt makes them advantages and helps to them. When they wraſtle with ſin, it would be too hard for a ſaint if Chriſt did not help them, and ſin would get the advantage over them; ſhould Chriſt but leave us in a temptation, we were undone, but Chriſt comes with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering unreſiſtable power, &amp; reſcues us from ſin, and brings us over to the loves of himſelfe.</p>
            <p>So alſo in affliction, the ſaints they moyle and toyle, and are even worne out in it, that they know not what to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:120033:34"/>do, that they are ready to give out, and lay downe all, then Chriſt he comes in and ſupports, and puts under his hand to ſtay the ſoule from ſinking; when our own ſtrength is done, then Chriſt comes in; nay, we many times wraſtle our ſelves into great ſtraits; Chriſt comes now and releaſes us; that when we loſe our ſelves, he gaines us, and wraſtles us into his owne loves and glory; he raviſhes us with his loves, and then alſo is he raviſhed with our loves as you ſee in this chapter.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they are made glorious by him, and with him, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſ. 68.13.</note> 
               <hi>They are like the wings of a Dove co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with ſilver, and her feathers like yellow gold,</hi> 'tis a metaphor, you muſt conceive taken from very pleaſant and glorious coloured Doves, to ſet out how Chriſt beautifies, and makes his ſaint glorious and amiable. The very ſame glory that is on Chriſt, is on a ſaint; Chriſt and a ſaint have not two different lives, two different
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:120033:35"/>glories; but both one and the ſame, ſayes the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Ioh 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>As he is, ſo are wee in this world.</hi> Brethren, the life of a ſaint is a miſterie, Chriſt and they live in the injoyments each of other, the life of a ſaint is internall.</p>
            <p>Surely friends, let me tell you, 'tis not knowne by partaking of fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and ordinances, although wee ought to partake of them, and hold them forth to the world, but the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the life of Chriſts conſiſts in the injoyment of Chriſts loves; ſo that the ſoule, is therein centred and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, as it is expreſſed 17.<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.23.</note> 
               <hi>Ioh. Thou in me, and I in them, and they in me, that they may be made perfect in one.</hi> All ſaints they are beloved with the ſame loves that the Father loves the Sonne, the ſame riches, the ſame life, the ſame love, the ſame glory is beſtowed on them.<note place="margin">Eph. 11.3.</note> We are now in this life, <hi>ſet in heavenly places in Chriſt,</hi> many thinke they ſhall have this life hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when they ſhall come to heaven:
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:120033:35"/>but thoſe that live this life, they are in heaven here, and <hi>ſit now in heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly places;</hi> and herein is the great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake among Profeſſours, they do not live in and with Chriſt here; they uſe ordinances, and hold forth a profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and here reſt; but for this heavenly life, this intimate uniting life, they looke not after it, they expect it not, they know it not, they live it not. Oh brethren! did you but know this life in experience, you would never reſt till you were in it, and were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by it, (for I pray mark) that this life muſt comprehend you, and not you it; you do not know, beloved, what manner of men you ſhould be, were you in it, <hi>it doth not yet appeare,</hi> ſayes the Apoſtle, <hi>what wee ſhall bee, but when he ſhall appeare in us, we ſhall ſee him as he is, we ſhall be made like him.</hi> Chriſts life ſhall be in us and we in him.</p>
            <p>We may talke of this life, but when we live this life, then we ſhall know
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:120033:36"/>it, then we ſhall be ſwallowed up of it; I my ſelfe knew it not what it meant, though I often ſpoke to you of it, till of late; and alas that we ſee and have of it, is but little ſmall gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merings of this life. In truth I now perceive there is but little injoyment of Chriſt in the world, this life is a hidden life, men talk of it, Chriſtians talke of it but alas how coldly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out affection, withoutlove, without o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelmings, which ſhewes they live without it, did you know this life, and did you live in the heart and loves of Chriſt, in the embraces of Chriſt, it would make us live othergueſſe lives then we do. Oh beloved, how full of loves and ſweetnes ſhould we be? how full of ſelfe-deniall? how much ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the good of others as your own? it does not make men of that harſh cenſuring, judging ſpirit, that is now ſo rife in the world, it does not make men ſo ſweld &amp; fly-blown with their own parts and with, the good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:120033:36"/>of others, if you had it, it would make you live farre above all theſe things. And ſo far as any mans life and comfort runs not parallel with theſe things, truly let him be never ſo great in profeſſion; in good earneſt he lives yet in the fleſh, and is not gotten into the life of Chriſt, Chriſt and they are not of one, but of two contrary ſpirits and lives. But oh the <hi>ſweet tranſcendent</hi> loves, joyes, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commings that Saints enjoy, who live with Chriſt, and in Chriſt, they live in loving, and love in living, Chriſt and they are of one ſpirit,<note place="margin">16. Eze. 6.</note> as 16 <hi>Ezek.</hi> 6. <hi>When I paſſed by thee, I ſaw thee pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted in thine owne bloud, I ſaid unto thee when thou waſt in thy blond, live, and I cauſed thee to multiply,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and then thy time was a time of loves,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then waſt thou comly through my comli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſe, that I had put upon thee.</hi> Chriſt makes his Spouſe beautifull with his owne beauty; but we for the moſt part thinke highly of our ſelves, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:120033:37"/>of our own beauty, and are comly to themſelves, through their own comli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and therin they glory; and moſt in the world runne this way in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, though in judgement they deny it; but he who is come up to Chriſt, to have his beauty put on him; his life and his injoyments; he hath put off himſelfe, he hath put of his own life, his own beauty, his own comlineſſe, and what ever injoyments come from ſelfe, all theſe he is crucified too.</p>
            <p>But this is a life none come too, nor none knowes what it is in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of it, but he that has it. So much for that Head. Wee come to a ſecond thing to be conſidered, that is, why they are called Doves, and that is in regard of the Saints property. The property of Doves is to be full of innocencie, and ſecondly full of love, and thirdly full of delight.</p>
            <p>Firſt, full of innocencie, a Dove is the harmleſſeſt creature in the world, ſo are the ſaints; the meekeſt, the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:120033:37"/>harmleſſeſt of all men; if they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled, they revile not againe; they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme not of the praiſings or revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of the world, becauſe they have no life in the world, nor of the world, as ſaints. If they have, they live be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low themſelves, they live apart from Chriſt; they are of ſo mortified a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in any worldly reſpect, if they live with Chriſt, and in Chriſt, that they cannot thinke any thing a gaine in the world, nor any thing a Loſſe: if they loſe any thing, houſes, lands, wives, children, honours, theſe they account no loſſe, becauſe to them they were no gaine; if they gain any thing, they count it not gaine, except they gaine their life in it; and that is God himſelf, chriſt himſelf; to have God in all they have, or elſe they account they have nothing, &amp; if they have nothing, if they live as I before ſhewed you, in the very boſome and heart of Chriſt, and in the mutuall embraces of each other, that they can ſay experimental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:120033:38"/>and feelingly, and enjoyingly, my beloved is mine, and I am his. This is their gaine, this is their all, and they have no thoughts of gaining in the world. For if they gaine theſe things and not God in them, they thinke themſelves looſers. 'Tis true, they love wife, children, friends, honours, ſo Chriſt be in them, with the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of his ſweetneſſe and loves, then they are well and at reſt.</p>
            <p>They think it no hard thing to bee reviled in the world, if God ſpeake love; let blind ſelfe-ſeeking, ſelfe-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing, men of the world ſay what they will. And therefore beloved friends obſerve your ſpirits; doe you find your ſelves moved and diſturbed by others revilings? ſo far you live in your ſelves; ſo far you are unmortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, uncrucified, you live not as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, according to the life you hold forth; if you did, you would ſee where their life is, &amp; how far below Chriſt, and how much in themſelves, that live
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:120033:38"/>in reviling &amp; defaming others; and in ſtead of being angry or to your ſelves and in your ſelves, returning like for like, you would pitty them, and pray earneſtly for them, that God would open their eyes, that they alſo may ſee upon what low and baſe principles they live and move.</p>
            <p>Againe, Doves are ſingle-hearted and full of love, ſo are the ſaints, as ſaints; they love, and delight in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; It is obſerved by ſome, of ſome Doves, and ſo of Hindes, that if their Mates had died, they were ſo affected with it, they would die alſo; ſuch a reſemblance is in the ſaints, they are full of love to each other, are ſenſible of each others ſufferings; they doe not ſeeke to undoe, vex, and defame one another, but pitty and helpe one another, they doe as they would bee done by; they will not requite evill with evill, as do the men of the world, and all thoſe that are not come up to the life of Chriſt to live as Saints, for
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:120033:39"/>they delight in loving; they live by lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and love by living, for 'tis ſaid of the Hindes and Doves, they have theſe three properties, firſt, they live by loving; ſecondly, they grow fruitfull by loving; and thirdly, they die with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loving. The ſaints do thus; they delight in love, they grow fruitfull by loving, and dye if they doe not love. 1. They live by loving, they are carried out in the firſt place in love to Chriſt, as the cauſe of their love; for Chriſts love to them, cauſes their love to returne to him; and they love Chriſt alſo in the Saints, theſe loves are the ſaints feaſt; they live by Chriſts kiſſing and embracing them, and by their kiſſing and embracing Chriſt, and alſo in kiſſing and embracing one anothers ſpirits; by communicating to each other their experiences and enjoyments of Chriſt; theres no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter joy, nor higher act in them then to act love, theſe are the dainties they feaſt on, then are they tranſcendent
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:120033:39"/>in their ſpirits, and then are they moſt full of Chriſt. Secondly, Doves are made fruitfull by loving, ſo are the ſaints; when thrive they more then when they have the ſweeteſt commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and are moſt open to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to each others injoyments, and ſo kiſſe and embrace each others ſpirits?</p>
            <p>No ſooner hath a ſaint kiſt the heart of Chriſt, but it is made fruitfull by that very kiſſe, by that embracement, and by that enjoyment; The very en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of Chriſt makes them fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. And they cannot be otherwiſe. They being once come to this, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy Chriſt they cannot be unfruitfull. Here is a ſaint then; his very love, his very nature provokes to fruitfulneſſe; if he be not fruitfull, what ever he may be taken for, as a great Chriſtian, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a great profeſſor; hee never yet enjoyed Chriſt, never yet knew what the loves, the overcomming tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent loves of Chriſt were.</p>
            <p>Fruitfulneſſe is made over to the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:120033:40"/>ſoule at that very inſtant; it is like the opening of the pores of the body, then the bloud interchanges and have free courſe and mingles it ſelfe through the whole body; this love of Chriſt (I tell you friends) it opens the pores of the ſoule, love and fruitfulneſſe runs from Chriſt into the ſaints in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terchangeably; as Chriſts heart is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to you, ſo is yours to him; there is a ſecret convayance to each other in the acts of loves.</p>
            <p>And thirdly they die without it, ſaints as ſaints, except they love they die; I pray obſerve, ſaints as ſaints cannot die, but their life dies, their joy dies, they live uncomfortably and as dying, as if they had no life. I ſpeak now in regard of actings; a ſaint when he acts not love, he dies; he may have ordinances, and uſe externall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes to Chriſt and with the ſaints, and yet he as good as dead, no more life in act and comfort then the men of the world, if the warm heart-bloud of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:120033:40"/>Chriſt doe not run, and have free courſe into his ſoule; the ſaint acts not as a ſaint; but yet he may act in religion &amp; worſhip; but, tis but to him ſelfe, &amp; to his own credit and honour, and eſteeme among men, or for ſome other ſelfe-end, and yet have no life as a ſaint. The new man and Chriſt is as dead, and acts not, and therefore it is, ſometime a ſaint has overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of ſpirit, mightily inlarged, his ſpirit has no bounds, another time he is bound up, ſtraitned, the pores of his ſoule are lockt up; he hath no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe of loves from Chriſt, and therefore has no breathings, no decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Chriſts loves to him, no experiences, he is wrapt up in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to himſelfe: and therefore this makes him, (the ſoule being as ſenſible of this as of death (for 'tis a death to him) this makes him to goe to Chriſt, and complaine heavily, oh! how he grones in ſpirit till he be revived, till his ſpirit, till his loves
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:120033:41"/>come into him againe, and cauſe him to act and live. Oh! ſayes he, let my Chriſt come into me or I die, I cannot live; 'tis true (ſayes he) here is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and here is a fellowſhip ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally; but whats all this, if my ſoule be frozen, if my heart be bound up; if I live within my ſelfe; if. I have not intercourſes and returnes of loves, from my beloved, I die, I die.</p>
            <p>Now beloved, would you have me make ſome uſe of this point from the particulars thereof; I hope you have done that your ſelves as I went along, but I will a little make out ſome uſes. I cannot be large becauſe of the time and my owne weakneſſe; and I would make it out to you of what I have found in my own experience; though I muſt confeſſe it is but lately, and no great light neither; there are depths, there are glorious tranſcendent truths, in theſe experiences; but oh! how dark, at how ſmall a crevice doe wee ſee? How ſhort doe we come? I tell you,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:120033:41"/>though I have many times ſpoken of theſe things, yet how coldly, no ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhings, no inlargings, no overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings of ſpirit, how bound up? truth is, I had the Theorie in my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and I thought I had pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed them, becauſe I knew them; but 'tis but new, 'tis but ſmall the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of them; but God wil reveale and lead on his ſaints from ſtep to ſtep; that they ſhall go from ſtrength to ſtrength, digging up fountaines till they appeare before the Lord in Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Profeſſors talke much of heaven, but I profeſſe they never were in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, nay never will be, if they come not to this life; you hope it may bee this life will bee hereafter. But I tell you, your heaven is here as well as hereafter in a degree: be not deceived to perſ wade your ſelves you are ſaints, and you are Chriſtians, and have not this life, we have deſcribed; ſo farre you are in your ſins, you are yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt, you are yet in your ſelves,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:120033:42"/>you are not come up to the life of a Chriſtian, to the life of a Saint.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſes,</hi> from the particulars; firſt, are the ſaints ſo happy in their priviled ges, that they are Chriſts Doves, and ſo precious to him? is it the priviledge and portion of the ſaints to be ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to Chriſt? then take this as the firſt conſectory, this will follow, if it be ſo.</p>
            <p>Then they will not long to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to the world; you will not bee troubled though the world, though men, though friends, though enemies regard you not; ſo you be precious to Chriſt, this is enough for you; what though ſuch a friend ſpeake evill of you? what thongh ſuch a Profeſſor loves you not; and there another pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour ſuſpects you, and you are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled; VVhy ſaints, where is your life, in the world or in Chriſt? if in the world, no marvell you are troubled; no marvell you are <hi>offended;</hi> if your life bee in Chriſt, (you will
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:120033:42"/>ſay) what matter; ſo Chriſt thinkes preciouſly of you; if you have the ſweet and mutuall embraces of Chriſt; and your ſpirits run into each other, and kiſſe and embrace each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, here would be your reſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, obſerve from the next particulars, is nothing in the heart of Chriſt, too good for ſaints? does Chriſt embrace, ſalute, kiſſe, raviſh, the ſaints in his tranſcendent loves? Does he endow them with the ſame glory he himſelfe hath with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? for I muſt put things together, ſtrength will not hold out to take them all ſeverally as the things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve. Have any of you felt theſe things in your owne experience? I do not aske you, if you have had the knowledge thereof in your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, but haue you enjoyed them, and found the loves of Chriſt, ſo large, ſo overcomming to your ſoules? doe you ſee and feele, that Chriſt thinkes nothing in his very
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:120033:43"/>heart too good for you? The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture indeed is very full to prove this, I need not cite them, but have you made proofe thereof? are theſe things ſo to you? are they proved by your injoyments? then I will tell you what it will worke.</p>
            <p>Firſt, nothing that you have will be too precious for Chriſt, Chriſts very heart, his life, his riches, his loves, his glory, is not too precious for you. And your very heart, your life, you will not think too precious for him, much leſſe your honour, your riches, your credit; I tell you friends, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will be too deare to part with, ſo you may be taken up to theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments; you will tread upon all as dirt, as dung, ſo you may gaine the loves, and embraces of Chriſt. Will friends, will honours, will parts, will ordinances, ſtand you in ſuch ſtead as the loves of Chriſt? will they lay you in the very heart and boſome of Chriſt? will they redeeme you from
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:120033:43"/>the law and ſet you free? will they take you from under the power of the killing letter, which threatned no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but death and hell? will they take all advantages to do you good, by ſin, by afflictions? will they come in and helpe you, when you are quite worne out? will they helpe you out in ſtraits? No, no, they will not, they cannot: but all they can doe, is but to lay you in their owne boſomes, they cannot helpe againſt the terrours of the Law; they take all advantages to doe you hurt, they cannot helpe you out of ſtraits, but rather helpe you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſtraits, &amp;c. The ſaints, as ſaints, they looke on all outward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts thus, and how then can they bee in love with them; they looke on them as chaffe, as ſtubble, as nothing; their life, their loves, their treaſure is in the loves of Chriſt, and having Chriſts heart, running out to them and theirs to his;<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.23.</note> 
               <hi>Thou in me, and I in them, and they in me:</hi> Thus much
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:120033:44"/>you hold forth by your profeſſion of Chriſt, and if it be ſo, then I wonder why ſomething of yours is too good for him; if you looſe your honour, your good name, your eſtates for him, you thinke much, you thinke Chriſt deales hardly with you; and well you may, if he beſtow not himſelfe upon you; but had you as good a thing in the roome of that you loſe, you would never repine; if Chriſt be ſuch happineſſe, ſuch riches, ſuch raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſo that he is better then all things elſe; whats the reaſon you ſticke ſo much upon the creature? whats the reaſon you come not off to this life? whats the reaſon that ye come no ſooner, make no more haſt, have no more longings to it? But friends, were you in the armes, in the embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſt, you would repent you came no ſooner into theſe joyes and loves; that you were no ſooner cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified to the fleſh, and to your ſelves. Oh! beloved, I tell you, you would
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:120033:44"/>ſleight all things as they ſtood in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to Chriſt. But as I told you before, they doe love wife, friends, children, but 'tis in Chriſt, as Chriſt appears to them, in them. But friends, where is your great boaſting of your profeſſion and Chriſtianity, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to Chriſt, if theſe things be ſo? If Chriſt take away ſtrawes and give Diamonds and Pearles, what cauſe haſt thou to complaine? If thou doſt complaine for the loſing of theſe ſtrawes, it is ſigne for all thy boaſting thou haſt no Pearles; but theſe ſtrawes, theſe nothings were thy Pearles and thy Diamonds.</p>
            <p>Againe, is a ſaint made glorious by Chriſt, and is Chriſt and his glory all one? then were you made glorious by Chriſt, you would be ſwallowed up in the loves of Chriſt; you could not live apart from Chriſt, but you ſhould live in Chriſt. You have heard this is your priviledge, as ſaints; you ſhall not live in one region, and Chriſt
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:120033:45"/>in another, but you ſhall injoy the ſame life, the ſame joyes, the ſame loves with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Againe, is the preſence of Chriſt in himſelfe? then 'tis not to be enjoyd elſe-where; 'tis not in fellowſhips; 'tis not in ordinances, ſimply conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; yet theſe ye are to uſe to hold forth the diſcipline of Chriſt to the world, yet not to reſt in theſe; theſe diſtinguiſh you externally from the men of the world; but you will be as of the world ſtill for all them, if you enjoy no more but bare ordinances. This I ſpeake, becauſe many ſatisfie themſelves in this, in receiving outwardly the ordinances, and that they are accounted Profeſſours, and ſequeſtred from the men of the world, and becauſe they are found in ſuch and ſuch fellowſhips, being well thought on by others; alas theſe will doe you no good; for all theſe you may have no more life then the men of the world. You ſee no man can
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:120033:45"/>live in the boſome of Chriſt, and in the glory of Chriſt, but hee is made one with Chriſt; Saints, they are not only made perfect hereafter; as moſt Profeſſours run away with that; but they are admitted and have ſome en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into heaven here; they live as Saints, they walke as ſaints, they trade as ſaints, they live with Chriſt; they walke up and downe in loves, love compaſſes them round about, they are ſwallowed up of loves; they live in loving, and love in living; ordinances are but ſhels; but ſaints while they are cracking the ſhell to others, they are eating the kernell themſelves, and live thereby. Alas friends, you may be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of all externall ordinances, you may ſubmit to Baptiſme, you may come into a right order of a Church way, you may frequently break Bread together, but whats all this friends? this is but the ſhell of the buſineſſe, the huske, the bone; but is Chriſt glorified in your ſpirit, (here is the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:120033:46"/>life) and you in his Spirit, here is the kernell, the marrow; doe you live as he lives? are you made one in ſpirit? truly friends, examine, and look wel to your ſelves, for mine owne part, often have I ſpoken to you, &amp; taught to you, that which I found not in experience; yet I thought I had; but truly I find now I comprehended them, yet I was not comprehended of them; I knew not what eating the kernell was, nor taſting the marrow, the ſweetneſſe till of late.</p>
            <p>Againe, are ſaints well and fitly called Doves, in regard of liveing in loves, and by being made fruitfull by loving, and in regard they cannot live except they love? then obſerve that the people of God, are an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent people; they are innocent to the Law; Chriſt hath fulfilled it for them, and freed them from the Law, and brought them to peace and liberty from under the power of the killing letter.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:120033:46"/>
            <p>Againe, are the ſaints no ſelfe-ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers but ſelfe-deniers? then I wonder what means that rough and rugged carriage in thoſe that ſay they live with Chriſt, and in Chriſt, and injoy Chriſt; &amp; yet their life is much in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to defame others, and to ſet up themſelves: This is not to live as ſaints, this is farre from the carriage of ſaints, this is not to live in loves, &amp; to grow fruitfull by loveing; the carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of a ſaint is (you have heard) to ſeeke anothers good as their owne: Theſe then live not in Chriſt; but they live in the world, Chriſt and they live in two contrary Regions; theſe declare they yet live in the Creature, in ſelfe, in fleſh: theſe ſeek for honour of men, and not of Chriſt; ſo they may but ſet up themſelves, it matters not what becomes of their brethren. As thoſe that love Honour or Riches or what elſe in the World, ſo they can but get them for themſelves, they care not how many ſuffer for it, ſo they
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:120033:47"/>have it: are theſe (beloved brethren) ſuch as live as Chriſt lives? thoſe that revile becauſe they are reviled, nay revile when not reviled; how farre is this below the practice of ſaints? ſuch men proclaime and hold it forth they are no ſaints in practice, what ever they would have the World or Gods people thinke of them.</p>
            <p>The ſaints, (you ſee) they underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue all mans reviling, it is to farre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them to revile againe, to returne evill for evill; you ſee they are paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive in ſuffering, but active in loving: the other are proud, ſelfe-ſeeking, ſelfe boaſting, and they yet live in the fleſh, and are not come to live in and with Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Againe, obſerve from the ſecond thing that the ſaints grow fruitfull by loveing and delight in loving, then they are not conſtrained by the law to duty, but they love it of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, it is no forced thing in them; they do not task and force them ſelves
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:120033:47"/>to obey Chriſt but it is their nature, and they work freely, their lives are in loving, and in loving they have their life. Till men come to live this life, theſe things, to all men elſe are a hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den miſtery; and if a miſtery no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell then men ſo much miſtake in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out this life, and what a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is, for no man knows it, nor hits it right but he that lives it, for all elſe, live and grope in the darke and few attaine to it.</p>
            <p>Some men ſay this is the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and ſome that is the Chriſtian, and it may be miſtaken in both, for they make Chriſtians according to their owne fancy; if he do but jump with them in opinion, this is enough to hold him up a Chriſtian, oh! he muſt needs be the godly man, and and yet ſee not that rule the word holds forth in the life, marrow, &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of it: but beloved it will be ſo, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man judges by what light he has; &amp; if his light be falſe or dark, ſo needs
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:120033:48"/>muſt his judgement be. Yet in my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience I ſee but (as it were) a dram of that weight of glory that is to be revealed upon the ſoons of truth.</p>
            <p>And I wil tel you what my thoughts are; I am perſwaded, ere long, God will pick out himſelfe a choiſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; now here is ſome what to do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Churches and ſelected Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, but you will ſee (if I miſtake not) ere long, Congregations pickt out of Congregations; of Men that have experience of this life of living with God. And the ordinances ſhall be yet more and more purified; and yet they not reſt in ordinances, but ſhall haue the marrow of ordinances: I ſay the time will come, that there will be a people who kiſſe and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace one another in ſpirit, and ſhall live in loving and in joying one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, farre more then ever, yet our eyes have ſeene.</p>
            <p>Wee ſhould now have further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to the next points, namely
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:120033:48"/>theſe, from the words, <hi>My Dove, my undefiled is one. Doct.</hi> 2. That Chriſts Dove is not a defiled, but an undefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led company. Thirdly, that Chriſts undefiled Dove is but one; though they be ſcattered and divided here to men, yet to Chriſt they are but one, where wee ſhould have ſhewed the folly of many in theſe dayes, that they ty their loves only to that congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted body of which they are in fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with; and if they differ in judgement from them, they have no love to them; neither doe they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them of the number of Chriſts one, undefiled Dove; this is groſſe ignorance, and proceeds from weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, pride, and folly; and is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed meere Antichriſt, and the fop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries of men: congregated, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congregated, ſo they bee Chriſts Doves, we ought to love them. But my ſtrength faileth me, and ſo I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you, and what hath been delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to the bleſſing of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:120033:49"/>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:120033:49"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PHIL. 4.11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I have learned in what ever eſtate I am therewith to be content.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt point from theſe words is this. <hi>Doct.</hi> That contenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is a Saints leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; firſt, let us ſee what a Saints conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is? Secondly, the benefits that flow from a Saints contenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Firſt what a Saints contentation is, it is this; to bee content with God, and in God in all conditions; herein is
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:120033:50"/>only a true reſt; if it be in any thing elſe but God, it is no true reſt; If honour, or pleaſure, or profit, or credit, or applauſe, or riches, or any thing beſides God doth give thee reſt; thy reſt and content is in the creature, and not in God: for then, as theſe things ebbe and flow, ſo doth thy content. But hee whoſe content is in God, his content is, as God ebbes and flowes to him; ſo that if he have God and enjoy him, hee cares not how the creature comes or goes. If hee have riches, and not God in them, he hath no true reſt.</p>
            <p>And on the contrary, if he have poverty, diſgrace, banniſhment, or impriſonment, and enjoy God, hee hath his reſt ſtill. Becauſe his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent is not in, and with the creature, but it is in and with God; Gods will is his reſt. Hee that lives in the will of God, hee ſees Gods will is beſt for him; and his will is ſo ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:120033:50"/>up in the will of God, and made one with it, that hee hath no peace but in this.</p>
            <p>And this life hee hath and enjoyes not by reaſoning himſelfe into this condition; as, for a man to ſay thus; this is Gods will, and I muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; it is but a folly to reſiſt his will; it muſt bee ſo, and I cannot helpe it; therefore I were better be content, then to fight and ſtrive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; for I cannot remove it, till God pleaſe.</p>
            <p>Now this is not the content of Saints, but that which reaſon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates to a man, which a man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out grace may reach; and in this content moſt are ſatisfied, and take it to bee a Saints ſubmiſſion, and contentation when it is not.</p>
            <p>But a Saints reſt, content, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, is not from reaſon; but from a ſweet enjoyment of God in every condition; ſo that in every
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:120033:51"/>condition, hee findes God ſo ſweet, ſo raviſhing, that hee concludes; theſe conditions are beſt for him, better then any other. And this man hee ſees really; that God chooſes his conditions better for him, then hee can chooſe for himſelfe; ſo that this man findes really, and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally, ſuch enjoyments of God, ſuch ſparklings of love, ſuch preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous experiences of grace ſcattered up and downe in thoſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that hee cannot wiſh them otherwayes, except the will of God be to change them, and to put him into any other condition better for him.</p>
            <p>For if hee deſire health, or honour, or riches, or parts, or any other condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and therein finde not God and his glorious out-goings in his ſoule, and experiences of his loves; hee hath no reſt: but poverty and the contrary hee deſires rather, ſo hee
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:120033:51"/>may have the enjoyment of his God in them.</p>
            <p>For I told you, it was God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and God in all things, and with all things, was the true reſt of Saints. His reſt is not in this and that, but God in this and that; ſo that whether hee have this thing, or that thing, if hee have not God in this, and that thing, he hath no reſt, not as a Saint; I pray obſerve that. I doe not deny, but many men may have a reſt, but it is not a Saints reſt, as a ſaint; and that which flowes from grace, and from the loves and embraces of God himſelfe.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:120033:52"/>
            <p>Whether it flow from reaſon (as I told you before) or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee from injoying the creature. As many men that live below reaſon, that live by ſence; they have a content and ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; becauſe they have the creature; riches, or honour, or credit, or beauty, or parts, and they are herewith content: truly friends, this is no better then a ſenſuall content; and this is farre ſhort of that content that comes from reaſon; and therefore, much more of that which flowes from God and grace; for he that hath it from God, and by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying that ſweetneſſe of loves
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:120033:52"/>that is in the will of God; hee lives with God, lives in God, is in the very boſome of God, in the very heart of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And hee that lives there; no marvell though hee regard not the motion and alteration of the creature; but as God alters to his injoyments.</p>
            <p>When hee enjoyes moſt of God, then hath hee the greateſt content, though hee have the leaſt of the creature; and when he enjoyes leſſe of God, then hath he the leſſe content, though never ſo much of the creature; and the reaſon is, becauſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without God, nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:120033:53"/>God can be his reſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for the good, and for thoſe benefits that flowe from this enjoyment, of God and from a Saints content.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Hee that lives this life, hee is free from the combuſtion of oppoſition; for when God doth one thing; and the will of man would have another, here now Gods will and mans, fight; and ruſh one againſt another, like two contrary ſtreames or ſeas, which will not mingle. Where theſe two wills meet, there muſt needs bee much trouble, and great combuſtion in their oppoſition; the man cannot be
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:120033:53"/>at reſt;<note place="margin">Iea 1.6.7.8</note> but as the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> ſayes, <hi>Hee is in a very unſettled, wavering condition, like a wave of the Sea carried and toſſed every way, and cannot receive any thing of the Lord, being double minded, and unſtable in all his wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee would have a reſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of God and the creature. And ſuch a man cannot receive any thing of God, in a ſaint-like way; till hee come to enjoy God ſingly and nakedly; hee can have no laſting, no true reſt.</p>
            <p>But did we reſt in God and not in the creature, wee ſhould
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:120033:54"/>be free from this combuſtion, and this alterity in our ſpirits. And ſo farre as wee want it, ſo farre wee are ſhort of a ſaint-like ſatisfaction and reſt.</p>
            <p>And where this content is not, there is that combuſtion In oppoſition, and reſiſting Gods will, (as I ſaid) like two migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Seas that daſh one againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; and where that is, there is a foame, froth, and filth caſt up which annoyes the man; <hi>A diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented heart, that caſt up mire and dirt;</hi> Much ſinne, froth, and defilement. And as the Apoſtle, ſaith; <hi>this man is unſtable in all his wayes, and carryed about with
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:120033:54"/>every wind of Doctrine.</hi> Every wind of Doctrine changeth his opinion; and certainly there is no man rightly eſtabliſht, and groundedly firme in his opinion, till hee come into this life, to live with God, and in God.</p>
            <p>But hee whoſe will is emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied into the will of God, hee lives with God, and in God; he ſits aboue all the Alterity of the creature; change this man from one condition to another, hee changes not, as his condition changes; throw him into any condition, which way you will, hee ſtill falls on his leggs.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:120033:55"/>
            <p>This is the man that <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes of, <hi>that he maketh to lye downe in greene paſtures and leads him beſide the ſtill waters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 37.4.</note> 
               <hi>he reſtoreth his ſoule and leades him in the path of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes for his Name ſake, and though he walke in the valley of the ſhadow of death he will not feare; thy rod and thy ſtaffe is with me. and they comfort mee,</hi> they ſee loves, and gaines, and proffits, and ſweet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences more precious then pearles in the very rods of God, and are fully ſatisfied with the goodnes of God. God ſpreads them a <hi>faire Table in preſence of their enemies, and their head is ſweetly anoynted with oyle, and their cup runneth over, like the oyle on</hi> Aarons <hi>head;</hi> which perfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth al Gods dealings, to them <hi>&amp; run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth downe to the very skirts of their garments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 133.</note> 
               <hi>and like the dew of hermon and as the dew on the mountaines of Zion, for there he commandeth the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:120033:55"/>bleſſing even for evermore,</hi> and this is that <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes off in the 37. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 4. <hi>Delight thy ſelfe in the Lord and he ſhal give thee the deſires of thine heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ 23.</note> Whats that thinke you? that you ſhall have riches, and plenty, and credit, and eaſe, and full tab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and great earthly poſſeſſions? No no, but that in the want or fullneſſe of theſe things, you ſhall have God to be your reſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; that your will and Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing united, you ſhall have no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires but whats agreeable to the will of God.</p>
            <p>This is that <hi>dwelling in the Land and being fed of God,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes in the 37. <hi>Pſ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For ſo long as we live on the creature, we cannot have this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall life, and theſe divine promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes made good to us; but of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, wee liveing on the creature,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:120033:56"/>wee muſt be ſubject to the troubles diſtraction and changes of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>As thoſe that live in any ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt needes be ſubject to the motions, Alterations and troubles of that element in which they live. As birds, or fiſhes: birds live in the aire, if the ayre change and be infected, ſo needes muſt they: or fiſh, if the element of water wherin they live, be poyſon'd or diſturbed ſo are they; and ſo it is in this; thoſe that live in the creature and with the creature: muſt needes ſimpathize, and bee ſutably qualified to the creature.</p>
            <p>But he that ſits above with God is above all change in the creatures element; hee is ſelfe-denied to the world, and all in the world.</p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:120033:56"/>
            <p>Againe, this is the way to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; ſo far as we are ſatisfied with God, and ſatisfied with truth; ſo far we live in perfection; I doe not ſay that perſon is perfect, or without ſin; no, but ſo farre as we live this life, ſo farre we come toward perfection, and live in perfection, and live with God; The new man carries us to God and perfection; it aſſends and carries us upward, to God and Chriſt: but ſo farre as we come not up to this life; ſo farre wee live below God, and are drawne downward to the Creature, to the World, to Hell-ward, to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell-ward: as one when he ſaw a Bird tyed with a ſtone to her Legg, as ſhe mounted to flee upward, ſtill the ſtone drew her downe to the Earth, and thereupon he fell a weeping; becauſe it did ſo fully repreſent to him his own condition, hee could not but weepe. Grace carries and drawes a man on to perfection; but the old man drawes downe to the Earth, to defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:120033:57"/>to deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Againe this conditon of a Saints reſt is a gathering condition; it puts him in a gathering way. I pray you obſerve it, this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the thriving man, he only is in a thriving way; this man is like to grow a rich man indeed. All our wayes are ſcattering wayes; if we live on the creature we gaine not, but ſcatter and loſe all; he that lives this life of a Saint, that God has taught him this leſſon, flowing from his own ſelfe, from the very heart of God, and the boſom of Chriſt; he gathers ſuch precious flowers of experience, and gaines ſuch precious Jewels and Pearles, that he counts himſelf rich in them, and in nothing elſe; If hee live beſide God, he lookes on himſelf as a man that ſcatters all; as a growing to be a banckrupt; one that has no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the rich gainings of grace;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>Godlineſſe with content</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>is great gaine.</hi> Ther's no true co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent but in gaines by grace, and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:120033:57"/>the rich experriences of Gods work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the ſoule; to ſee which way corruption comes to be cruſified, and he kild to the world and the world to him; to ſee how his power and life comes in, and to obſerve the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous outgoings of God, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his glorious and Godlike pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings with his ſoule; this ſatisfies and compoſes his heart; to ſee how ſweetly God hath conquered his ſoule, and brought his will into ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that was ſo raging, ſo rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. <hi>Then he counts it all joy to fall into divers te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations;</hi> knowing, &amp; finding by experience, <hi>that the trying of faith worketh patience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 13.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>to be intire wanting nothing;</hi> and ſo farre as he comes into this life of perfection? <hi>to rejoyce in that he is made low; and he that is of low degree</hi> in the creature, <hi>to rejoyce in that he is made rich in God, and high in God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro. 5.4.</note> and he ſees how <hi>patience bringeth forth experience, and experience hope, and hope maketh not a ſhamed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:120033:58"/>
            <p>We will now come to ſome ſhort uſes and conſectories from this point, and from the benefits thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe the firſt;</hi> Is contentation a ſaints leſſon? is a ſaints ſpirit a ſatisfied ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? then ſo far as any one of us have not a ſatisfied ſpirit, ſo far we have not a Saints ſpirit, ſo far we are not ſaints; So far as we are not ſatisfied, content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, at reſt and compoſed, ſo far wee are ſhort of God, and have not the life of God; ſo far as we live not with God and in God; For this is held out to us in the very nature of God; God is in himſelfe at reſt, ſerene, compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; no diſtraction in the Creature touches him, he ſits above; that is, hs is free from all changes and all al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations in the world; ſo is that man ſo farre as he is a Saint, being united and made one with God; though he live among the creatures, as God has his being in and through all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, yet he is not altered by the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; So has this man as he is a ſaint,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:120033:58"/>not his joy, his life, his riches, his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the creature, but in and with God, above all creatures.</p>
            <p>Againe, is a ſaint as he is a ſaint, of compoſed ſatisfied ſpirit, compoſed of one ſpirit; for that is promiſed in Jer. <hi>I will give them one heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 32.39</note> 
               <hi>and one ſpirit?</hi> then he is not of a devided diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented ſpirit; hee is not troubled with thoſe wiſhings and wouldings as men below are. Oh that I had this condition or that condition: but (ſaies he) let any condition come, ſo I have God in it: God is my reſt and not the condition; be it riches, or health, or the beſt condition wherein the men of the world, and ſo farre as we are unregenerate, to think therein is reſt; oh ſaies one, had I but ſuch a ones condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, ſuch Lands, ſuch Honours, I could be contented and ſatisfied; oh ſaies another, had I not ſuch enemies, were they but cut off&amp;overthro wne, I ſhould have reſt; this is not the temper of a Saint as a ſaint; But he ſayes I have
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:120033:59"/>found that promiſe fullfild? <hi>I have the deſire if my heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 37.4.</note> my reſt is in God, and I cannot tell what to wiſh other then I have, what I have I would have; and what I would have I have: if thou art not come to this, thou haſt a devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded heart.</p>
            <p>Some men they are ready to ſay, and bleſſe themſelves in their conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſay, I thanke God I am conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; but wherein is thy content? thou haſt a good eſtate, and thou haſt the deſire of thy heart in the creature, thou haſt rare parts, or thou art ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured among men, &amp; herein thou art ſatisfied; and thou thinks this is a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious content; thou doſt not murmur, but bleſſeſt God for thy condition; alaſſe, this is but ſenſuall, this is but na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; if thy content were right, it would not be in the creature but in God; Should God wheele thee into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother condition, and wheele away theſe outward contents, then where will be thy comfort? And ſome who
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:120033:59"/>are gone a little higher, they can boaſt and ſay, I bleſſe God I am content; <hi>I</hi> am in poverty, in diſgrace, in priſon, &amp;c. <hi>I</hi> am perſwaded to ſubmit to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe it is ſo and it cannot be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waies; tis therefore better to bee content, then to fight againſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, except <hi>I</hi> could help it; this is but reaſoning a mans ſelfe into content, this content is not a Saints content; that is, to be content as ſeeing an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency in this condition; as ſeeing beawty, and loves,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 68.24.</note> and the glorious outgoings of Gods proceedings; <hi>They have ſeen thy goings O God who art in the Sanctuary, therefore the Virgins love thee;</hi> oh the ſparkling pearles and diamonds this ſoule diſcovers; experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences worth all the world; <hi>he ſells all that he hath to purchaſe this field where theſe jewells are.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 13.46.</note> But he that reaſons himſelfe to reſt, he is not ſatisfied nor content, though he ſaith, he is; for he ſees no loves, no joyes no gatherings, no riches in theſe conditions, he longs
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:120033:60"/>to have the conditions changed, if he could; he longs not for the experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the condition; But the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſayes, let me have thoſe ſweet experiences, and then any condition; for thoſe experiences are my riches, my life; <hi>I</hi> am now in a gathering way; now <hi>I</hi> ſee my riches come in; inſtead of envying and wiſhing for others conditions, thou wouldſt ſay: no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions like mine, no riches like theſe riches, no credit like this credit; what to lie in the very boſom and heart of of Chriſt; That whether he continue poverty or remoove it, honnor or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move it, ſo that <hi>I</hi> may have my joyes, my experiences, the injoyment of my God, for therein is my reſt.</p>
            <p>For this man, a Saint, is contented with God, and not with ſomething done by God; but with God in all conditions; As we may look upon the Spouſe in the <hi>Cant.</hi> let her be <hi>buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feted</hi> ſo ſhe may but have <hi>her beloved</hi> ſhe cares not;<note place="margin">Cant. 5.7.</note> ſhe will through all for
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:120033:60"/>him; &amp; the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, <hi>tell him, I am ſick of love;</hi> if ſhe have not her beloved, give her what you will, riches, honour, parts, ordinances; oh ſhe cryes out, what means all theſe things, you mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake my diſeaſe, <hi>I am ſick of love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you be content, what means this wiſhing and woulding; what meanes this picking and chuſing your condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? what meanes ſo much envy of others conditions, if you ſee them but before you? Does a man that has a thouſand pounds, that has pearls and diamonds, envie him that has but a peny or pibble ſtones<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> tis never ſeene. Therefore wee may conclude thou haſt no Pearles, no treaſure; thou haſt not found <hi>the field wherein is the pearls;</hi> thou haſt not found God in health, and God in ſickneſſe, God in riches, and God in poverty, and God in parts, and God in want of parts, and God in all.</p>
            <p>I pray obſerve this; nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents the ſoule, but that which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:120033:61"/>the ſoule in all conditions, in all its wants; riches, honour, beawty, &amp;c. doe not anſwer the ſoules wants, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God be in them; it muſt be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſutable to the ſoules nature; that muſt be Godlike and ſpirituall, elſe it will not feed the ſoule; theſe terrene things feed but ſenſe not ſaints; A child delights not to play, but with children, not with old men; ſo the ſoule delights not to play with crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which are all below God; but it loves God, and delights in God, in the loves and imbraces of God, aud God delights in the imbraces of ſaints, their imbraces are mutuall.</p>
            <p>Take this as another conſectory from this Doct. Is a ſaints reſt &amp; ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in the injoying of God? then ti's not not a ſeſſation of any outward accommodation, can ceaſe a ſaints content and ſatisfaction; for his joy, his reſt lives, when all outward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts dies. As <hi>Habac.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Allthough the figtree ſhall not bloſſome, neither
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:120033:61"/>ſhall fruit be in the Vine: the labour of the Olive ſhall faile, and the fields ſhall yeeld no meat, the flock cut off from the fold, and their ſhould be no heard in the ſtalles. Yet I will rejoyce in the Lord: and joy in the God of my ſalvation. The Lord God is my ſtrength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, If ſo farre as a ſpirit is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and at reſt, its ſo farre like <hi>God;</hi> then thoſe that profeſſe themſelves ſonnes and daughters of <hi>God</hi> and are not content; they are not like <hi>God;</hi> they are not ſonnes and daughters of <hi>God;</hi> they are not the Image and off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of <hi>God;</hi> for thoſe that are <hi>Gods</hi> ſonnes, and borne of <hi>God,</hi> they are like <hi>God,</hi> hold forth <hi>Gods</hi> Image; and ſo farre as we come ſhort of this wee hold forth the Divells image; and we are no farther to account our ſelves the ſonnes of <hi>God,</hi> then as wee are begotten of <hi>God,</hi> and ſo far as we are content with <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> in all things; Elſe we are begotten of the will of man, and of the will of fleſh,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:120033:62"/>and not of the will of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, dos this contentation of a Saint give him abilitie to be in a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering way in all conditions; then thoſe that thrive not by all conditions ſo farre they are no Saints, but they are in a ſcattering, undoing way; they are ſcatterers and loſers in all conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, becauſe they injoy not <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Contentation with <hi>God</hi> is our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt gaine, and the reaſon is; becauſe this fixes a mans heart to his own por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is <hi>God</hi> alone; and ſo farre as we run out from <hi>God</hi> to the creature for content, ſo farre we run out to <hi>ſtrange women,</hi> to commit adultery, and play the harlots, as Jer. 3. ſhewes, <hi>Thou haſt played the harlot with many lovers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>yet retutne againe unto me ſaith the Lord. Surely as a wife treacherouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly departeth from her huſhand, ſo have you dealt treacherouſly mith me, oh houſe of Iſrael.</hi> All things but <hi>God</hi> is ſtrange women.</p>
            <p>Againe, is he that is content with
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:120033:62"/>
               <hi>God</hi> free from the combuſtion of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; then we gather further; that no condition is croſſe to this ſpirit; we commonly cry out of croſſes; from men, from friends, from enemies; croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by <hi>Kings,</hi> and croſſes by <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and why is all this? croſſes in a <hi>Presbiterian</hi> way, and croſſes in an <hi>Independent</hi> way, and why? the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe our ſpirits are not laid levell to all conditions; to ſee all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions equall to him, that lives with and in <hi>God.</hi> truly friends think of this ſeriouſly; our croſſes are not without, but all our croſſes are from within; we have wills of our own, which croſſes; and daſhes againſt <hi>Gods</hi> will in our conditions; and hence is the croſſe: for were my will and the conditions ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and laid levell, here would be no croſſe; And hence it is we are ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet: the working of our wills and conditions being ſo thwart and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that they caſt up fome, mire, and dirt; and hence it is that we are ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:120033:63"/>we are not fixed, but carried up and downe with every wind of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; hence it is, that ſo far as we are content with any thing below <hi>God,</hi> we are lyable to the change and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of the nature of all things.</p>
            <p>See then friends wherein a ſaints content and reſt lies; tis <hi>God</hi> in friends, <hi>God</hi> in relations, <hi>God</hi> in all outward ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations? you ſee allſo how great a good and benefit ariſes from this life; When they faile <hi>God</hi> ſtands; we are free from the combuſtion of oppoſition; that man has no croſſe, no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is rough to him; ye are in a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering way, ye ſhall grow rich; your heart ſhall be fixt and not carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with every wind of doctrine and opinion; Laſtly, this fixes your heart faſt to your own portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is <hi>God</hi> himſelf. And thoſe rich injoyments of his glorious outgo-ings;<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.24.</note> 
               <hi>they have ſeen thy goings o God, even the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of my God, and my King even in the Sanctuary.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
